Guide to the William Louis Gaines Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Louis Gaines papers
1937-2004
MS 1858
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
The papers of William Louis Gaines contain correspondence, topical files, and journals. Journals comprise the great majority of the collection and cover almost his entire life. The journals, often over six hundred pages per year, provide comprehensive details about the organizations where Gaines was employed, analysis of current events, personal information, and much introspection.
Gaines, William L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of William Louis Gaines, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Monticello, Indiana, William Louis Gaines attended Bowling Green State University (B.A., 1946) and the University of Nebraska, Lincoln (M.A., 1947). In 1951, he completed his doctoral dissertation in history at Yale University. For five years following, Gaines worked as an assistant political attache at the United States Embassy in London. In 1956, Gaines entered the field that he would become most associated with, international education. He served as executive secretary at the U.S.-U.K. Education Commission until 1961, when he became associate director of Commonwealth Fellowships. In these positions, Gaines administered scholarship programs that encouraged international exchange. From 1962 to 1970, Gaines was director of education at the African-American Institute, where he worked with both African and American universities. For the subsequent four years, he was a professor of history at the University of Nebraska at Omaha, concurrently serving first as dean of academic affairs, then as dean of international studies. From 1974 until his retirement in 1992, Gaines was President of the Institute of European Studies and the Institute of Asian Studies. Throughout his life, Gaines promoted intellectual achievement through international exchange. He died in February 2005.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Louis Gaines contain correspondence, topical files, and journals. Journals comprise the great majority of the collection and cover almost his entire life. The journals, often over six hundred pages per year, provide comprehensive details about the organizations where Gaines was employed, analysis of current events, personal information, and much introspection.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by type of material.
Journals; Gaines, William L.; African-American Institute; Institute of European Studies
- Biographical, 1981, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Africa consultation, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence
  - General, 1945-1972, 1993-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 3 - 5)
  - Hennig, Calvin [and Ruth], 1973-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
- D-Day 50th anniversary, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Institute of European Studies, 1983-1984, 1992-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- United States Information Agency (USIA): Namibia, 1993-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 11 - 15)
- University of Nebraska, Lincoln, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Yale Graduate School Alumni Fund, 1992-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17 - 18)
- Miscellaneous, 1966, 1991, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Journals
  - 1937-1944 (Box 4, Folder 20 - 25)
  - 1945-1951 (Box 5, Folder 26 - 29)
  - 1952-1956 (Box 6, Folder 30 - 38)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 39 - 47)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 48 - 52)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 53 - 62)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 63 - 70)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 71 - 80)
  - 1971-1973 (Box 12, Folder 81 - 90)
  - 1974-1976 (Box 13, Folder 91 - 101)
  - 1977-1980 (Box 14, Folder 102 - 114)
  - 1981 (Box 15, Folder 115 - 118)
  - 1982-1984 (Box 16, Folder 119 - 131)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 17, Folder 132 - 137)
  - 1988-1990 (Box 18, Folder 138 - 151)
  - 1991-1994 (Box 19, Folder 152 - 159)
  - 1995-1997, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 160 - 166)